Atiq ul Rehman

Email: rehman652@gmail.com

Objective:

To apply my functional safety and automation leadership and technical skills to a team environment to play a significant role in advancing the business, improving facility performance and protecting lives and the environment.

# PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

13 years of engineering experience in DCS, SIS and F&G systems, Functional Safety, project management, project engineering, operations support and reliability. This experience was obtained in the oil & gas refining/petrochemical sector, mainly working with multinational and multicultural organizations. Hands on experience of the project/safety life cycle with thorough knowledge of control and safety systems, programming, process instruments, control valves, process control strategies, safety critical devices and management of change.

#### PROFESSIONAL STRENGTHS

FUNCTIONAL SAFETY	AUTOMATION /CONTROLS/INSTRUMENTATION	LEADERSHIP
<ul><li>TUV Certified FSE</li><li>Chevron SIS Trained</li><li>Fire &amp; Gas</li></ul>	<ul> <li>DCS/SIS/PLC Programming</li> <li>SCADAmanagement</li> <li>Field instrumentation/Calibration/Testing</li> <li>Field Modification/Validation</li> <li>FEED (Front End Engineering Design)</li> <li>Commissioning</li> <li>Functional Testing</li> </ul>	<ul><li>Project Management</li><li>Team Development</li><li>Training</li></ul>

#### PROFESSIONAL SKILLSDETAILS

- Hands on Experience on the following:
- DCS: Yokogawa Centum CS 3000, Centum VP
- SIS(ESD&F&G): Yokogawa Prosafe-RS, HIMA, Invensys (Triconex) TMR based system.
- <u>PLC Programming:</u> IEC1131-3 programming in (Ladder Logic, Function Blocks, Sequential Function Charts, Structured Text), PID Loop Control, etc.
- <u>HMI:</u> Graphic Builder (Yokogawa), Factory Talk View SE/ME, RSView 32 and Supervisory Edition, Wonderware InTouch.
- Control Valves: Fisher and other brands of control block valves.
- <u>Field Instruments:</u> Detectors, analyzers, vibration and speed systems, BMS, Boiler control, control schemes, controller tuning. Instrument maintenance.
- Well Head Control: Oil and Gas wellhead control and safety systems.
- <u>Industrial Software:</u> Experion studio, station and all others, Visio, MS project, In-tools.
- Industrial Networks: Vnet IP, RS232/485, ControlNet, Ethernet, Foundation Fieldbus, Modbus.
- Asset Manager: Plant Recourse Manager (Yokogawa's Plant Asset Manager)
- <u>Historian:</u> Yokogawa Exaquantum
- Analytical Abilities:
- Technical Root cause Analysis and Engineering design reviews.
- <u>Process Safety and Functional Safety:</u> HAZOP, JSA, PSSR, incident investigation and RCA, MOC Management experience.

# Atiq ul Rehman

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Tengizchevroil (Chevron) - Kazakhstan (July 2012-March 2015, October 2018-June 2020)

# **Automation Engineer**

- Risk Assessment and Mitigation
- Investigations and follow-ups on Safety and Process systems modifications and recommendations.
- Various Automation Projects FEED, Consultation, Engineering, Commissioning and implementation.
- Project execution with optimal resources while keeping and maintaining highest safety standards.
- Coordination and Liaison for cross-functional teams.
- Supervise and lead a multicultural team, mentor and develop local manpower and create expertise.
- Technical Consultant on Automation modifications, upgrades and new projects in detailed design engineering, procurement, testing for ESD/Fire & Gas and Process Systems (Cathodic Protection Systems, Corrosion inhibitors, Multiphase Flow meters, Downhole Pressure Gauges, etc.)
- Review and develop C&E's
- SCADA development, implementation and commissioning
- Review design, engineering & construction documents including but not limited to P&ID, Instrument Index, specifications, Instrument Layouts, Instrument Hookups, Instrument wiring Diagrams, Control & protection narratives, Logic Narratives, Logic Diagrams, Cause & Effects Matrix, Complex Control Loops, Network Architecture, Control System interconnectivity and data interface drawings and documents.
- Site Acceptance Tests (SAT), Loop verification and Testing.
- Support field instrumentation team in installation, commissioning and maintenance.

## INTECH Process Automation - USA/Pakistan (May 2012-September 2018)

## Sr. Design & Application Engineer

- Project management and Project Lead.
- Internal Testing, DVT (Design Validation Testing) and FAT.
- SAT, Pre-Commissioning, Commissioning, startup and training, after sales O&M services.
- DCS, SIS, F&G, PLC Engineering & development of various Oil & Gas, onshore and offshore projects.
- Review, design, engineering & construction documents including P&ID, control & protection narratives, logic narratives, logic diagrams, Cause & Effects matrix, complex control loops, network architecture, control system interconnectivity and data interface drawings and documents.

#### Projects

- Basrah Gas Company (Shell) Iraq (Yokogawa DCS, SIS, F&G. Honeywell TGS)
- Galeota PWT Project (Schlumberger/BP) Trinidad and Tobago (Allen Bradly Control Logix)
- Crude Operating System (Schlumberger/PetroMonagas) Venezuela (Allen Bradly Control Logix)
- OML-100 ICSS Upgrade Project (Total) Nigeria (Yokogawa DCS)
- Tengizchevroil (Chevron) Kazakhstan CFM, GSD, MS, Trunklines (Allen Bradly PCS, HIMA SIS/F&G)

# Yokogawa (Pakistan (UEC Pvt. Ltd.), Singapore, Saudi Arabia) (July 2007-April 2012) System Engineer /Service Engineer

- Management of clients in petrochemical, oil and gas and Fertilizers sectors.
- Preparation of project organizational chart, schedule, IO loading Philosophy, BOM and FDS for projects.
- Developing and configuration of Control/Safety System and Network.
- Yokogawa latest DCS, ESD, F&G application development.
- Integration of latest systems with Yokogawa legacy/older systems.
- Inhouse Engineering design, FAT, iFAT, SAT, commissioning and startup.
- Performing Preventive Maintenance (PM) activities on DCS/SIS and handling day-to-day issues during normal operation of plant.
- Performing Shutdown Maintenance (SDM) activities during shutdown of plant.
- Comprehensive Yokogawa trainings to Operations before start-up for smooth custody transfer to operation.

# Atiq ul Rehman

#### Projects

- Saudi ARAMCO Saudi Arabia (Yokogawa DCS/SIS Services)
- Maaden Fertilizers Saudi Arabia
- Fatima Fertilizers Pakistan
- Meher Gas Field (OMV)- Pakistan
- BYCO Oil Refinery Pakistan
- Pakistan Refinery Limited (PRL) Pakistan
- DESCON Oxy-Chem Pakistan

### **EDUCATION**

#### **Technical Education**

 B.E Mechatronics and Control Engineering University of Engineering & Technology Lahore, Pakistan 2003-2007

# AFFILIATIONS, TRAININGS

- TÜV (Rheinland): Certified Functional Safety Engineer for the application area "Safety Instrumented Systems"
- HIMA SILworX HIQuadX training
- Registered Professional Engineer, Pakistan Engineering Council.

#### GENERAL INFORMATION

- Currently hold work permits for Kazakhstan.
- I am fluent in written and oral English and Urdu languages, and have quite an understanding about Arabic, Russian and Kazakh languages.

References		
Name	Position held while working with me	<u>Relationship</u>
Bradley Warr Bradley.Warr@BasrahGas.com Phone: +964 7808329872 +61 449686939	PACO Engineer (TA3) - Shell	(Ex-Supervisor)
Richard Facer richard.facer@shell.com Phone: +964 7809279199 +61 407487283	PACO Engineer - Shell	(Ex-Supervisor)
Muhammad Qamber Abbas smqamberabbas@hotmail.com Phone: +12819656104 +77029038983	Technical SIS Consultant - TCO	(Ex-Colleagues)
Petar Slavov peter.slavov@gmail.com Phone: +77012835962	FE I&C Advisor - TCO	(Ex-Colleagues)
Dave Burrows daveburr@absamail.co.za Phone: +7756725816	FE Lead Engineer - TCO	(Ex-Supervisor)